Officially is ס"ט, Samech Tes, we pick up at the top of
ס"א ע"ב, Samech Aleph Amud Beis, and we are introduced the idea
of the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that an
אילונית, aylonis, a woman who is not just unable to have kids,
I mean we haven't really defined the physical characteristics of an אילונית,
aylonis, but a woman who is more like completely out of the
category in some ways in which her body has developed and so
on, it's like childbirth was never part of the equation, and he
says that woman would be forbidden to a כהן Kohen because of
a, she'd be in the category of זונה, zonah, and coming from
a very particular perspective that sex without the context of procreation, even
the bigger, larger context of procreation in some theoretical way, is considered
to be an act of זנות. znus. And that's going to be
very important in terms of ongoing discussions, it is certainly not the
only rabbinic attitude towards marital sex. Then the גמרא Gemara quoted the
position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that a כהן Kohen
cannot marry a קטנה, ketanah, and it's trying to figure out why.
And what's significant is it does not suggest the idea of זונה
zonah there, like what, every קטנה ketanah girl is a זונה zonah
until she becomes able to have children or even sort of calling
it a type of ביאת זנות be’as znus because again, somebody who
can in the if that's in the offing and in larger part
of the larger context, the גמרא Gemara does not even suggest that
that would be part of the conversation. So that's not the issue.
So what's it about? So the first suggestion we have is that
רבה Rabba said because combination of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה’s Rabbi Yehuda idea that an אילונית aylonis
is forbidden to a כהן, Kohen, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
is concerned with minority opinions, חייש למיעוטא, chaysh l’miyuta, it's not minority
opinions, minority likelihoods, small little percentage likelihoods, and therefore don't marry a
קטנה ketanah because she might grow up to become an אילונית. aylonis.
Okay, so that's the גמרא’s Gemara רבה’s Rabba suggestion. Now let's see
if the גמרא Gemara challenges this. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, וכרבי מאיר
מי סבר לה,
u’k’Rabbi Meir mi
savar lah, does he really hold like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So
the line starts with the word סבר לה, savar lah, it's about
fifteen lines down from the top. וכרבי מאיר מי סבר לה, u’k’Rabbi
Meir mi savar lah, does he really hold like רבי מאיר? Rabbi
Meir? והתניא, ve-hatanya, but we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, קטן וקטנה
לא חולצין ולא מייבמין דברי רבי מאיר. katan v’ketanah lo choltzin v’lo
meyabmin divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that a קטן
katan and a קטנה, ketanah, we've, it's so funny that we've dealt
with all these things of יבום yibum and now in a totally
different tract and we have yet to deal with this question about
whether you have to be an adult or not when you do
יבום. yibum. Thank you. So he says that a minor, a קטן
katan or קטנה, ketanah, boy or girl, cannot do חליצה chalitzah or
יבום. yibum. So אמרו לו לרבי מאיר, amru lo l’Rabbi Meir, they
said to him, יפה אמרת שאין חולצין, yafeh amarta she’ein choltzin, yeah,
it's a good point, yeah, they cannot do חליצה. chalitzah. Why? איש
כתיב בפרשה, ish kasiv b’parsha, because it says איש לא יחפוץ האיש,
ish lo yachpotz ha’ish, if the man doesn't want to. ומקישין אשה
לאיש, u-makkishin ishah l’ish,
and since it talks about her and connects her to him, so
therefore, the same way the word איש ish is understood to mean
an adult, so he has to be an adult and she has
to be an adult in the act of חליצה. chalitzah. אלא מאי
טעמא אין מייבמין, ella mai ta’ama ein meyabmin, but why not יבום?
yibum? Because since יבום yibum is not about intent, right? We looked
at the beginning, whether מזיד, meizid, שוגג, shogeg, even אונס ones and
רצון ratzon and the whole thing, it's just about the simple act
of sex. And since we have been seeing that we consider it
halachically to be an act of sex when the girl is over
three years old, and we haven't said it yet, but when the
boy is over nine years old, so it's an act of sex
and you don't need כוונה, kavana, so why can't it work? להקים
שם מת,
lakim
shem meit, right? So a קטן katan can't do that? What?
להקים שם מת, lakim shem meit, right?
So a קטן katan can't do that?
Yeah, but that doesn't have to be immediately possible either. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא מאי טעמא אין מייבמין, ella mai
ta’ama ein meyabmin, אמר להו קטן שמא ימצא סריס. amar lehu katan
shema yimtza saris.
Your, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said, yeah, there's no intrinsic reason why
they can't, but if it turns out later that the minor is
actually a סריס, saris, right? So also like not just sterile, but
somehow סריס saris is more about the entire, you know, a larger
physical aspect of him. Again, we're not going to unpack that now,
but anyway, and that's considered completely out of the category of having
kids. וקטנה שמא תמצא אילונית, u-ketanah shema timtza aylonis, and the young
girl may be she turns out to be an אילונית, aylonis, and
maybe one of them will turn out to be a type of
a person that in seen like in a in terms of their
very physical being are out of the category of having kids, and
therefore that's not the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum in those cases,
ונמצאו פוגעין בערוה, v’nimtzu pog’in b’ervah,
and then if those, if that's true, there wouldn't have been a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, and if there was no מצוה mitzvah
of יבום, yibum, then it would be an act of, right, forbidden
sex of עריות arayos because it would be brother's wife. Okay, so
that's what he said. He says technically they could, but again, not
just if it happens to be, he doesn't say שמא תמצא עקרה,
shema timtza akarah,
or שמא ימצא עקר, shema yimtza akar, but so that's important to
note that does not necessarily mean that just because sex isn't possible
procreationally on practical. that it's not the מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum.
But somehow the person of an איילונית ailonit and a סריס, saris,
and we haven't exactly defined why, are seen as more categorically excluded.
And that's also the idea of why before we were saying an
איילונית ailonit is a זונה, zona, it's in a fundamental categorical way.
And he says and therefore that might happen and therefore they can't
do it now because then retroactively they will have had they will
have had forbidden sex because of אשת אח. eshet ach. You might
say they were be minors when they were forbidden sex, but maybe
one would have been an adult and the other would have been
a minor. So the adult would have been really transgressing, right? Understand
how right? So the adult would have been transgressing in that case
even though the other person wasn't an adult. Also it's interesting is
that
it's
suggesting is that at the age of בר ובת מצוה Bar u-Bat
Mitzvah you'll know the issue of איילונית ailonit or סריס, saris, right?
You won't know yet the question of what? Which you didn't know
before? Right. So those are things to be thinking about when we
get to more specific descriptions of what איילונית ailonit and סריס saris
is. Because the question about whether somebody is fertile or not is
not something you can know at the age of בת מצוה, Bat
Mitzvah, right? And anyway this woman's been married to the brother for
twenty years, so maybe there's a good reason to think she's not
fertile. Right? So right? It's not that she's just בת מצוה, Bat
Mitzvah, and nevertheless that's the classic case of יבום. yibum. Okay, so
therefore it's something very specific about איילונית ailonit and סריס saris and
something somehow that can be identified or begin to be identified at
the age of בר ובת מצוה. Bar u-Bat Mitzvah. No, it's an
ערוה ervah because there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibum. And once
there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, it's not an ערוה ervah
because of an איסור issur of sex with a סריס. saris. When
there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, then it's the איסור issur
of brother-in-law. That's or sister-in-law. Okay, did you have a question before?
No.
We're assuming that that a קטן, katan, that it's the קטנה ketanah
or the קטן katan can have sex?
Yes,
I said that. Yeah, that the same way we've been assuming that
it's considered a הלכה halachic act of sex by a girl even
over three years, by a קטן katan we say even over nine
years. So for example if a married woman has sex with a
boy who's nine years and a day and she does it intentionally,
so even though he is not punishable yet, you know, for her
it's an act of adultery and it's completely punishable, right? Or say
if it were case of incest or whatever. As long as once
it's an act of sex because even if one of the parties
is underage, the other party is culpable. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. That's רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir position. חייא שמיותא
Chaya Shmiyata געזונטהייט. gezundheit. ותניא, ve-tanya, okay, fine. ותניא קטנה קטנה מיאנה
בו באמת ואינה חולצת דברי רבי אלעזר. ve-tanya ketana ketana me’ana bo
be-emet ve-eina choletzet divrei Rebbi Elazar.
But look, I'll show you that רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar doesn't hold
of רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, 'cause רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar says that
a קטנה ketana can do יבום, yibum, not חליצה, chalitza, not חליצה
chalitza 'cause she's categorically excluded 'איש כתוב בפרשה מקשינן אשה לאיש', ish
katuv ba-parasha makshinan isha le-ish, okay? So just in order to do
חליצה chalitza you have to be an adult and just that's one
of the criteria. But for יבום yibum he says okay. So he's
not concerned with רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. So you cannot construct a
רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar position combining רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda number
one. He's clearly not concerned about the minority possibility. Point number one.
And even though we've already proved our point, we're going to prove
that point that he doesn't hold of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda either.
ורבי יהודה מי סבר ליה? ve-Rebbi Yehuda mi savar lei? You really
think he'll take רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraisa,
'זונה זונה כשמה'. zona zona kishmah. And now we have a nice
little list of positions in the תנאים Tannaim about it's so fascinating
without almost any גמרא Gemara exploring what is the biblical category of
זונה zona for a כהן. kohen. So the first one says 'זונה
זונה כשמה', zona zona kishmah, literally a זונה, zona, which is not
very helpful. What do you mean a זונה? zona? A זונה zona
is what it says, it's זונה. zona. דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rebbi
Eliezer. That's what רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer said. Now you and I
might think that means okay, a prostitute, a woman who's standing on
the street corner and prostituting herself. But then 'רבי עקיבא אומר זונה
זו מופקרת'. Rebbi Akiva omer zona zu mufkeret. No, זונה zona is
a woman that is
like הפקר, hefker, like doesn't know, indiscriminately having sex with people. So
maybe it's different, maybe it's not she's
selling sex, but she's still completely what's the word? Not licentious, licentious,
promiscuous, right.
So now רשי Rashi says on 'זונה כשמה', zona kishmah,
where's רשי? Rashi? 'כשמה', kishmah, if you look at רשי Rashi about
eight lines down in the narrow lines, 'לשון טועה שטועה מתחת בעלה
לאחרים דלרבי אליעזר אין זונה אלא אשת איש', lashon to’eh she-to’eh mi-tachat
ba’alah le-acherim de-le-Rebbi Eliezer ein zona ela eshet ish,
okay?
Which is very interesting. I certainly wouldn't have thought that's what it
means 'זונה כשמה', zona kishmah, but he says זונה zona is a
woman who committed adultery. That's the way רשי's Rashi reading 'זונה כשמה'.
zona kishmah.
Right, exactly. But I'm saying it's funny that not, you know, the
statement 'זונה כשמה' zona kishmah doesn't help so much. So רשי's Rashi
explaining it in a very different way than I might have explained.
רבי מתיא בן חרש אומר, Rebbi Matya ben Charash omer, 'אפילו הלך
בעלה להשקותה ובא עליה בדרך עשאה זונה'. afilu halach ba’alah le-hashkotah u-va
aleha ba-derech as’ah zona. Any act of forbidden sex, even an
act of forbidden sex that occurs within the context of marriage. She
is suspected of having committed adultery, so there's this איסור issur that
even her husband can't have sex until it's cleared up. And it's
only an איסור issur because of a doubt. It's not like a
fundamental status of her as a person, right? And nevertheless even transgressing
that. Transgressing that איסור issur would make her a זונה. zonah. Okay?
Or one
might—so that would make her a זונה. zonah. Now there's another sort
of minor איסור, issur, minor whatever, it's a prohibition but it's in
the context of marriage, and nevertheless a woman is still forbidden to
her husband, and that would be מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushato, right?
Whose wife—whatever. It's just מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushato, right? But that we
can't use as an example because that woman is already a גרושה.
grusha. It's not an interesting case for a כהן. kohen. Okay? So
this is a case that is completely within the context of a
completely legitimate marriage and nevertheless it's a forbidden act of sex that
makes her a זונה. zonah. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi
Yehuda says, זונה זו אילונית, zonah zu ailonit, which is what we
saw in the משנה. Mishna. וחכמים אומרים, v'achamim omrim, אין זונה אלא
גיורת ומשוחררת ושנבעלה בעילת זנות. ein zonah ella giyoret u'meshuchreret v'shenib'ala beilat
znut. So the בעילת זנות beilat znut is number one, more limited
than מתיה בן חרש Matya ben Charash because that would only be
an איסור כרת issur kares or an איסור כהונה. issur kehuna. Okay
that, although if it's an איסור כהונה issur kehuna she's already out
from that perspective, so maybe not—let's bracket that, that might be more
about a חללה. chalalah. Okay, but anyway, that's for the חכמים. Chachamim.
Okay? Whereas what we discussed that yesterday, or we discussed it at
the beginning of
today. And גיורת ומשוחררת giyoret u'meshuchreret is, as we said, either concerns
about having had sex with a non-Jew or a fundamental assumption of
how to look at the non-Jewish world. Okay, and that's the חכמים.
Chachamim. Okay? So so far though that's all very nice, but we're
not up to רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar which is the one that
we're trying to figure out whether רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or not in terms of this of an
אילונית. ailonit. So now we said like this: רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer, Rabbi Eliezer says—now there's a question whether before it was
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Before we were
saying רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was the one who said זונה כשמה.
zonah k'shma. And here it's רבי אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Elazar omer, Rabbi
Elazar says, פנוי הבא על פנויה שלא לשם אישות עשאה זונה, panui
haba al pnuyah shelo leshem ishut asaa zonah, any act of extra-marital
sex. Okay? Not any act of forbidden sex, but he's even more
extreme than רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says it's promiscuous. He says
doesn't matter promiscuous, you could have a committed relationship but it's extra-marital
sex, that makes her a זונה. zonah. And anyway, for our purposes,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who's the one we're trying to nail down
about why he says that a כהן kohen can't marry a קטנה,
ketana, he says it's זונה כשמה. zonah k'shma. With זונה כשמה zonah
k'shma you could either take to mean literally a prostitute or you
could mean a woman who's committed an act of adultery like רש״י,
Rashi, but it certainly is not אילונית. ailonit. Okay? Now so we're
still trying to now understand so why does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
say a כהן kohen can't marry a קטנה. ketana. Now before we
get to the next answer, again I just want to reiterate here
you have fascinating like a whole wide range of different opinions of
what is this category of זונה zonah in the תורה, Torah, you
know, with no גמרא Gemara analysis on it, and it has very
strong implications for כהנים, Kohanim, you know, nowadays, exactly that, and particularly
the whole issue of גיורת giyoret as we mentioned. I do want
to mention one thing about פנוי הבא על פנויה. panui haba al
pnuyah. If you take a look at the little תוספות, Tosafot, right,
non-marital sex or extra-marital sex, the little תוספות Tosafot פנוי הבא על
פנויה panui haba al pnuyah says, לאו דווקא נקט פנוי וכל שכן
נשוי. lav davka nakat panui v'chol shekein nasui.
It's not just that they both are single. Okay? It means even
if they're both single, but it would certainly be a problem if
he's married. Why? שמזנה על אשתו דחשובה זונה shemizanneh al ishto d'chashuva
zonah
because if he's married then it's even worse, then he's cheating on
his wife. Okay? So it's saying even if they're both single and
unattached and even if it's not הפקר, hefker, it's committed relationship, it's
still זונה. zonah. So what I found fascinating about this תוספות Tosafot
is that it sort of is a very much of what we
sort of express as a modern sensibility about the idea of adultery,
right? It's his partner, you know, right? But הלכתית, halachically, right, the
marriage only limits the woman, it doesn't limit the man, right? And
there—we were with a polygamous sort of הלכה, halacha, if the society
was changing, at least הלכה halacha allowed for polygamy. So what do
you mean cheating on your wife if you're having sex with another
woman? I mean, you know, just read what we're reading about יעקב
Yaakov and his four wives and so on. So it does—I think
it's fascinating that he says, yes, it's even more זנות znut because
you're cheating on your wife, which maybe reflects the reality in אשכנז,
Ashkenaz, you know, and חרם דרבנו גרשום Cherem de-Rabbeinu Gershom and the
whole thing about the norms of a monogamous relationship, that he's calling
that being מזנה על אשתו. mizanneh al ishto. So I thought that
that was quite significant. Okay, yes.
See because to me when I hear זונה, zonah, like it doesn't—it
sounds more like a descriptive person who's like that as opposed to
a descriptive one act kind of thing. Right, okay, that's sort of
like where I'm—I agree.
So that in a way אילונית ailonit is even better because that's
totally about the person. So you're saying maybe you don't understand how
a single act of forbidden sex—yeah, I understand that. But the problem
is saying well it's a person who generally, I don't know, like
sells her body, like where exactly when does that status start, when
does it end, how many times does she have to have done
it or whatever, that's why, you know, if you say one particular
concrete act does it, it's much more quantifiable. Okay, and now the
גמרא Gemara continues, says like
this: אלא אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, ella amar Rav Adda bar
Ahava, הכא בכהן גדול עסקינן, hacha be-kohen gadol askinan, talking about a
כהן
גדול. kohen gadol. Now remember... Kohen Gadol also according to many can't
marry a בוגרת. bogeras.
Sorry, הכא, hacha, right, why
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says a כהן Kohen can't marry a קטנה.
Ketana. בכהן גדול עסקינן. B'kohen gadol askinan. So לאימת קני לה? l'eimas
kani lah? So now he can't marry a בוגרת bogeras and he
also can't marry a קטנה. Ketana. Why? Because when is he going
to acquire her, meaning he's assuming that she's married off not by
the father. She's married off by, let's say, herself. You have a
קטנה, Ketana, emancipated or whatever, she goes ahead and she marries herself
to a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Oh, well then they're having sex—he's
having sex with her, right, before there's real קידושין. kiddushin. So לאימת
קני לה? l'eimas kani lah? When will he acquire her? When will
there be קידושין? kiddushin? לכשתגדל, Lich'she'tigdala, when she becomes an adult. At
that stage, בעולה היא, be'ula hi, she's already a woman who is
a non-virgin. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, מחלי לב. michlei lev. רבא
Rava said that was like a non-thought of—מחלי לב michlei lev means
מבלי לב, mibli lev, like you said that without thinking. That's—we can't
be talking about that. אי דקדשה אבוה, I de-kadsha abuha, what's the
case? If the father married her off, מהי שעתא הוא דקניא לה,
me-hee shata hu de-kanya lah, then they're married and obviously then it's
totally fine. ואי דקדשה נפשה, Ve-ee de-kadsha nafsha, she married herself off,
הא רבי אליעזר היא? ha Rabbi Eliezer hi? What, it's only רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ולא רבנן? ve-lo Rabbanan? Of course everybody would agree
that if they're not married and they're having sex and then they
get married, she's a בעולה. be'ula. Now of course it would have
been interesting to explore the case about what if the mother and
brothers marry her off? Right, what would, you know, but okay, but
that presumably would be the same. I mean it might not make
it ביאת זנות—we bi'as zenus talked before about having the rabbinic קידושין
kiddushin redefine it whether it's ביאת זנות bi'as zenus or not, but
it would still make her a בעולה be'ula when it's time to
get married halakhically. So the גמרא Gemara says רבא Rava said that
would not be a unique position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. אלא
אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, לעולם בכהן הדיוט עסקינן. l'olam b'kohen hedyot
askinan. We're going back to a כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. דחיישינן שמא
תתפתה עליו. De-chayshinan shemma tispateh alav.
And what we're concerned about is don't marry her because maybe she
will be seduced and therefore by another man, and therefore she will
be an אשת איש eshes ish and a זונה. zona. Okay, so
אי הכי, ee hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, ישראל נמי? Yisrael nami?
Yeah, so then
no—even a non-כהן Kohen shouldn't marry a קטנה Ketana because we're assuming
that under age will be more easily seduced. So he says no,
פיתויי קטנה אונס הוא, pityu'ei Ketana ones hu, which is our—which is
the very reasonable position, right, which we have you know in secular
law as well, which is—which is called a statutory rape. Okay, now
of course we have statutory rape if the girl is like 16
or something. Certainly when the girl is under 12, statutory rape makes
a, you know, a complete amount of sense, say there was no
what degree of רצון ratzon can we really be talking about there?
And obviously we would see that as abuse and as rape. So
that's what he says. So therefore, ואונס בישראל משרא שרי. ve-ones be-Yisrael
mishra shari. So if she's married to a non-כהן Kohen and somebody
manages to seduce her and have sex with her, then she'd be
מותרת mutteres to her husband because it's considered an אונס, ones, right?
And it's considered non-volitional. But if it's—she's married to a כהן, Kohen,
it doesn't matter whether it's volitional or not and she'll be forbidden
to her husband. So that's one answer. רב פפא אמר, Rav Papa
amar, בכהן גדול, b'kohen gadol, back to a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
והאי תנא הוא דתניא, Ve-hai tanna hu de-tanya, it's the following תנא
Tanna who teaches: בתולה. Be-sulah. יכול קטנה? Yachol ketana? Maybe he marry
a קטנה? Ketana? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: אשה. Ishah. It says והוא
אשה בבתוליה. ve-hu ishah be-visuleha. אי אשה, Ee ishah, if she's an
adult woman, יכול בוגרת? yachol bogeras? Maybe fully mature? תלמוד לומר: Talmud
lomar: בתולה. be-sulah. And for him, בתולה be-sulah often means a, you
know, a נערה, na'arah, נערה בתולה. na'arah be-sulah. So בתולה be-sulah means,
or complete בתולים, be-sulim, not בוגרת. bogeras. So but somehow for him
it also means—not exactly clear, but somehow it also means not a
קטנה. Ketana. So, I'm sorry, אשה ishah means not a קטנה. Ketana.
So אשה ishah means not a קטנה, Ketana, but בתולה be-sulah means
that the hymen is a completely in its—you know—unchanged. So what's that
spot in the middle between being a woman and the hymen being
unchanged? הא כיצד, Ha ketzad, יצא מכלל קטנות ולא בא לכלל בגרות?
yatza mikhlal katnus ve-lo ba'a likhlal bagrus? And therefore it's a נערה.
na'arah. So according to this, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can only
marry a woman between 12 and 12 and a half, a girl.
Right, a different
answer, a different answer. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר, Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar, האי תנא הוא דתניא, hai tanna hu de-tanya, it's the
following תנא Tanna where we taught: בתולה. Be-sulah. אין בתולה אלא נערה.
Ein be-sulah ella na'arah. בתולה Be-sulah is only a
נערה. na'arah. וכן הוא אומר: Ve-chen hu omer: והנערה טובת מראה מאד
בתולה ואיש לא ידעה. Ve-ha-na'arah tovas mareh me'od be-sulah ve-ish lo ye-da'ah.
So of course you might say if it has to say בתולה
be-sulah it means that נערה na'arah doesn't communicate that, but nevertheless he's
saying that those are normally seen as indicating the same status. Okay,
same idea though, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has to marry only
a נערה. na'arah. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now last—okay, so
that's the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that a כהן Kohen
can't marry a קטנה Ketana or a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can't
marry a קטנה Ketana for whatever reason. Back to the—ending up the
סוגיא, sugiyah, רבי אליעזר אומר. Rabbi Eliezer omer. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi
Eliezer Omer פנוי הבא על הפנויה שלא לשם אישות עשאה זונה Panuy
Ha-ba Al Ha-pnuyah Shelo Leshem Ishut Asah-ah Zonah that a woman is
a זונה Zonah for a כהן Kohen if she's had extramarital sex
even if they're both single. אמר רב עמרם Amar Rav Amram אין
הלכה כרבי אליעזר. Ein Halakha Ke-Rabbi Eliezer. We don't rule like that
position. Now is it רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or רבי אלעזר? Rabbi
Elazar? רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar seems to be right. אין הלכה כרבי
אלעזר Ein Halakha Ke-Rabbi Elazar like the position we just quoted, excuse
me, I misstated. And therefore that's very important, you know, because as
I said, nowadays a כהן Kohen is getting, you know, when כהנים
Kohanim are getting married, if the woman has had sex with a
non-Jew, it's a real issue, you know, it's a very serious problem
and those things come up not infrequently. But according to רבי אלעזר,
Rabbi Elazar, if she had, if she's ever had sex with anyone,
you know, in non-marital context, then it would, then she'd be אסורה
לכהונה. Asurah Likhunah. So we do not פסקן Pasken that way.
What about the איילונית? Aylonit? Is she אסורה לכהונה?
Asurah Likhunah? I don't know. Okay, I don't know because we פסקן
Pasken like the חכמים Chachamim that a זונה Zonah is only this
category. Okay, now, now because we mentioned the issue about marrying an
איילונית, Aylonit, a כהן Kohen marrying an איילונית Aylonit and whether איילונית
Aylonit is in the זונה Zonah category, and also that introduced us
to the idea about non-marital sex, about sex, marital sex in the
non-procreative context is considered to be זנות Zenut or not, and specifically
we're dealing with the whole issue of פרו ורבו, Pru Urvu, which
is now a perfect segue into this משנה Mishnah to discuss פרו
ורבו. Pru Urvu. So the primary place in the גמרא Gemara that
discusses the מצווה Mitzvah of פרו ורבו Pru Urvu is not in
קידושין Kiddushin and not in כתובות Ketubot but in יבמות. Yevamot. Okay,
so which is interesting. You know, it's interesting, if you think about
it, קידושין Kiddushin is more about the act of קידושין Kiddushin itself,
right,
the act of the giving of the ring or whatever it wasn't
a ring in time of the גמרא Gemara but anyway, כתובות Ketubot
is more about the state of נישואין, Nisuin, right, the second stage,
the חופה, Chuppah, the act of חופה Chuppah and the being married
and the reciprocal obligations and so on. And יבמות, Yevamot, in addition
to being about ייבום, Yibbum, is a lot about personal status and
also things relating to sex. Right, we had the whole discussion about
what constitutes an act of sex etc. and therefore in also related
way we're getting to the topic of the מצווה Mitzvah of פרו
ורבו, Pru Urvu, although this easily could have been in כתובות. Ketubot.
So let's take a look.
לא יבטל אדם מפריה ורביה, Lo Yivatel Adam Mi-piryah Ve-rivyah, a person,
a man should not stop from having children אלא אם כן יש
לו בנים Ela Im Ken Yesh Lo Vanim until he has children,
okay, which is a very funny way of phrasing it. Why do
we say like when are you יוצא Yotzei the מצווה Mitzvah of
פרו ורבו? Pru Urvu? But maybe it means because פרו ורבו Pru
Urvu it's not like taking a לולב Lulav and an אתרוג, Etrog,
right? I mean some people are trying for a very long time,
so it could be saying don't stop trying. You know, we've tried
for a long time we're not having kids. Oh you don't stop
trying or you don't start making efforts to have it happen. Like
or let's say a person is married to a woman for twenty
years, his wife dies, right, which is like a classic ייבום Yibbum
case. Don't sort of, you know, you still have the מצווה Mitzvah
of
פרו ורבו. Pru Urvu. So it's dealing with the phase don't stop
until, as opposed to you're יוצא Yotzei when. Okay, so you still
have your obligation of פרו ורבו Pru Urvu is incumbent until you
have children. Now how many children? בית שמאי אומרים שני זכרים, Beit
Shammai Omrim Sheni Zecharim, two males, ובית הלל אומרים זכר ונקבה, U-veit
Hillel Omrim Zachar U-nekeivah, male and female, שנאמר זכר ונקבה בראם, She-ne'emar
Zachar U-nekeivah Bera'am, male and female he created them, so which indicates
that the purpose of פרו ורבו Pru Urvu for בית הלל Beit
Hillel is what? You know, why is זכר ונקבה בראם? Zachar U-nekeivah
Bera'am? That's not in the מצווה Mitzvah of פרו ורבו. Pru Urvu.
I mean, פרו ורבו Pru Urvu is somewhere in those פסוקים Pesukim
nearby, but it's not exactly in the מצווה Mitzvah of פרו ורבו.
Pru Urvu. So what's that indicating for בית הלל? Beit Hillel? That
the purpose, what's the purpose of פרו ורבו? Pru Urvu?
What? Well why would anyone anyway say the מצווה Mitzvah of פרו
ורבו Pru Urvu is a boy and a girl? In order to
continue populating the world. Now you could just say everybody should have
two kids and the law of averages it'll all work out, right?
Which is true, right? So if you think about it communally. What?
As opposed to?
Not really if it was like what happened in China,
right?
Oh but
naturally, naturally if you naturally have kids, two kids and you don't
manipulate, what
he's doing perhaps is
maybe
in a male-dominated society or where male children are preferred, it's necessary
to
underscore that you have to have a girl. And we'll get to
that in terms of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Okay, but right, but
so A, it's to continue to populate the world, but also by
quoting זכר ונקבה בראם, Zachar U-nekeivah Bera'am, you could go a little
bit further, exactly, it's like imitatio dei, like competing, like being like
God, not just achieving the goal that there are enough men and
women in the world and the world continues to be populated and
achieving the ציווי Tzivui of פרו ורבו ומילאו את הארץ Pru Urvu
U-milu Et Ha-aretz to continue to have the world filled and populated,
but also to be sort of replicating that original divine act of
creation and creating male and female. So that makes a lot of
sense according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. What do the בית שמאי
Beit Shammai say? Two men, right? Certainly it's not about continuing the
act of populating the world, that doesn't happen if everybody stops at
two men, although I tried to do the averages, I'm sure Charlie
could do this, this would be a fun assignment. If everyone keeps
on having kids and everybody stops once they have two boys, what
will be the distribution of boys to girls? Okay, it's a fun
math problem, but it's not as totally skewed as you would imagine,
right? Because sometimes you start with two boys, sometimes two girls, a
boy and a girl, anyway, but it still would be a skewed
population. So obviously בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. has
a different idea what the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו peru urvu
is about. Okay, so we will and Dov already mentioned the issue
about sort of a male-dominated society in China and places where boys
are preferred. We'll take a look.
I even think you can say that it's like replicating yourself and
if the מצוה's mitzvah on the man and if it's the רבנן
Rabbanan then there's a harm from there.
Alright. Maybe. I don't see how you get two.
פרו ורבו. Peru urvu.
Alright. פרו ורבו. Peru urvu. More than one. Okay, that's interesting. That's
interesting. Yes.
What is modern child mortality rates? I think the accepted numbers for
repopulation is 2.1 per couple. Right. children. 2.1. Why?
Oh because of the cases of stress and illness and infertile and
whatever.
And people who die before
before... 2.1. Right.
If everybody has a 2.0 children then you have a declining population.
Ah, but even according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you're not always
having
2.0. You're בית הלל's Beit Hillel clearly it's going to be more
than two because many people will start off with two boys or
two girls.
Or two girls and that would make it two.
No. 50% of people will stop at two when you have boy
girl or girl boy. The other 50% who have two boys or
two girls will have to have three. So the actual average will
be at least, I have to do the math, but at least
something like either 2.5 or 2.25. I think 2.5 or something. Right,
Charlie, is that right?
I'm sorry, I was just looking it up.
If everybody stops at a boy and a girl, right?
Or they stop at two boys. Either way they're going to more
because what if they have two girls and then they have to
keep going, right?
Right, but if they have two boys they have to keep going
according to בית שמאי... Beit Shammai... בית הלל.
Beit Hillel. Right, so with either opinion you're going to have more
than an average of two.
I know. That's what I'm saying. That's what I'm saying. But you
actually have, according to בית הלל Beit Hillel you probably have 2.5,
right?
I'm looking it up right now. Okay. No. Okay, I think it's
a negative
binomial game.
Alright, fine. Okay. So anyway, fascinating questions. But I think that's a
good point that I never stopped to think about, which is not
just the division of the population, but what exactly would be the
birth rate that would come out of that. But no, even according
to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you're having clearly like a 2.25 or
2.5 birth rate. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
היש לו בנים, Ha-yesh lo banim, so if somebody has kids, מפרו
ורבו בטל, mi-peru u-rvu batel, the implication is then you can stop
worrying about having more kids. By the way, that's also important because
it just says stop. Like is there a מצוה mitzvah to have,
is two a minimum? Is there a מצוה mitzvah to have more
than two? You know, a קיום מצוה, kiyum mitzvah, a bigger מצוה.
mitzvah. Obviously have very large families nowadays, particularly in, you know, חרדי
Chareidi communities and so on. Is that part of the מצוה mitzvah
of פרו ורבו? peru urvu? So that's another important question that we
have to ask about the nature of the obligation beyond the minimum.
But the גמרא's Gemara saying that the משנה Mishnah sounds like don't
stop until you're יוצא. yotzei. Once you're יוצא, yotzei, you can stop.
But מאישה לא בטל, mi-ishah lo batel, stop having kids but you
can't, speaking to the man, not worry about being married. מסייעא ליה,
Mesayeia lei, that's the way it's inferring. מסייעא ליה לרב נחמן אמר
שמואל, Mesayeia lei le-Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, this supports Rav Nachman bar
Shmuel. אמר רב אדא, Amar Rav Adda, who says, אף על פי
שיש לו לאדם כמה בנים, Af al pi she-yesh lo le-adam kama
banim, even though a man already has a couple of kids, אסור
לעמוד בלא אישה. assur la'amod belo ishah. If his wife died or
they got divorced, no, he has an obligation to be married. That's
separate from
procreation. Important, right? Before we're talking about sex only in the context
of procreation. This isn't sex, this is marriage. And nevertheless he says
even once the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו peru urvu is no
longer relevant, there's an intrinsic value of being married. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, as
the verse says, לא טוב היות האדם לבדו. lo tov heyot ha-adam
levado. It is not good to be alone. There's an intrinsic value
of human
beings being in marriage, being connected to another person and the state
of marriage is an intrinsic good. It's important to note that because
another way it's framed elsewhere is, you know why it's important for
a man to be married even if he's already had kids? Because
otherwise
what will happen?
It's probably good for him to be in a sexual relationship and
not to have thoughts.
Right, otherwise he'll have problems about זרע לבטלה zera levatalah or sexual
transgression. There's a way of saying you should be married to make
it very instrumental and not an intrinsic good. So this is a
very important גמרא Gemara that it sort of says beyond kids, marriage
is an intrinsic good.
Although if you look at history, men have not been very good
in general,
even when they are married. Okay, that's a separate conversation, but hopefully
better when they are. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like that.
So again, very important גמרות Gemaras in terms of thinking about the
sex in a procreative context, marriage in a procreative context or a
non-procreative context. Okay.
Why don't they quote the... I don't remember the phrase, but that
a woman prefers to be married than to... Right. טב למיתב טן
דו. Tav le-meitav tan du.
But here it's about responsibility, not preferred. The גמרא... Gemara... טב למיתב
טן דו. tav le-meitav tan du. Okay. The גמרא Gemara says like
this. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, others say, היש לו בנים, ha-yesh lo
banim, we want to read the משנה Mishnah the following. If you
have kids, בטל מפרו ורבו. batel mi-peru u-rvu. No, that's not the
implication of the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah is once you have
kids, you can forget about the whole thing. בטל מפרו ורבו Batel
mi-peru u-rvu ובטל מן האישה. u-vatel min ha-ishah. And maybe you don't
have to stay being married. Sounds like just okay, then you're done.
Okay, fascinating how you could read opposite things out of the משנה.
Mishnah. So נימא תהוי תיובתא דרב נחמן אמר שמואל, Neima tehvei tiyuvta
de-Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, maybe that's a contradiction to Rav Nachman bar
Shmuel because Rav Nachman bar Shmuel says because I, let me sort
of explain what the גמרא's Gemara saying. It's not just a textual
דיוק. diyuk. How do you stop having kids in a society which
has no effective forms of birth control, right? How do you stop
having kids? The only way you stop having kids is either stop
having sex, which nobody is suggesting is people are going to be
doing, A because of human nature in the context if they're already
married, A because of human nature and B because it's a central
obligation of marriage. So the only relevance would be if the man
is no longer married, his wife has died or divorced, and it's
discussing whether he needs to remarry or not, right? So the question
of whether you still have to be trying to have kids in
a society where there's no birth control, what's the conversation? And why
don't you just say the conversation, you know, if I'm married and
having sex with my wife, of course we're still trying to have
kids. So the only relevance of that conversation is when he's not
married whether he has to remarry. Okay, whether he has to get
married again. So therefore the first way of reading it is, okay,
you don't have to get married again in order to worry about
kids, but you still have to get married again. And the other
way of reading it, no, if it's telling you I don't have
to worry about having kids anymore and right now I'm not married,
what it's telling you is I don't have to get remarried.
Yes, there were contraceptives back in Talmudic times although we've lost them
today. And second, coitus interruptus significantly reduced the fertility rate in France
in the 19th century.
Okay, but there's a whole question about that and whether that's הלכה
Halakhah or not. Okay, fine, but that's a good point. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says נימא תיהוי תיובתא, nema tehei tiyuvta, so if
you're telling me no kids that it's implicitly saying no wife, so
this let us say is the contradiction of רב נחמן אמר שמואל?
Rav Nachman amar Shmuel? לא, lo, no, it's not a contradiction. אין
לו בנים נושא אשה בת בנים. ein lo banim nosei isha bat
banim. No, no, no, because what it's saying is there's still a
way to be married and not have kids, which is how old
is your wife or, right? So if you are if you don't
have kids then when you're getting married you have to marry a
fertile woman. יש לו בנים yesh lo banim if you do have
kids, maybe you still have to get married, but when I'm telling
you you don't have to get kids, what I'm telling you is
נושא אשה דלאו בת בנים nosei isha delav bat banim that you
can choose to marry a woman who's not fertile. Okay, so I'm
not telling you you don't have to get married, but I'm telling
you you don't have to marry a woman that is fertile, that's
what it's saying. Okay, and נפקא מינה, nafka mina, תוספות Tosafot says
like why do you need another נפקא מינה? nafka mina? You just
gave me a נפקא מינה, nafka mina, but the נפקא מינה nafka
mina is also למכור ספר תורה בשביל בנים limkor sefer Torah bishvil
banim that we're going to see later that the מצוה mitzvah of
פרו ורבו pru urvu is so great that you would even sell
a ספר תורה sefer Torah in order to allow you to get
the funds to try to get married and so on. And that
would only be in the context before you're יצא המצוה. yatza hamitzvah.
But after you're יצא המצוה, yatza hamitzvah, when it says בטל מפריה
ורביה batel mi-pirya ve-rivya what it means is that you don't have
to go ahead and like sell a ספר תורה sefer Torah and
you don't or you're not allowed to do that in order to
in order to be מקיים mekayem the מצוה mitzvah once you're already
מקיים mekayem it, but it does not mean that you do not
have to be married. There's a value of being married regardless. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says the משנה's Mishnah's vague is about the
מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו, pru urvu, it's vague about the intrinsic value
of marriage, and its reading the משנה Mishnah to affirm either way
that it's definitely important to be married regardless of the מצוה mitzvah
of having kids, and the only question is about like whether you
have to make sure that you're able to have kids or not
or what type of allowances do we give to enable the marriage,
even in terms of selling a ספר תורה. sefer Torah. That's the
only relevance. All right, now moving on. בית שמאי אומרים שני זכרים.
Beit Shammai omrim shnei zecharim. Now you get to the definition of
פרו ורבו. pru urvu. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says two males.
So מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? mai ta'ama de-Beit Shammai? Good question. What
we were asking, what's the reason of בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? So
ילפינן ממשה. yalfina mi-Moshe. We learn from משה. Moshe. דכתיב בני משה
גרשום ואליעזר, de-chtiv bnei Moshe Gershom ve-Eliezer, which is not a מאי
טעמא mai ta'ama of the type of question we would ask. It's
sort of like where, you know, what's their biblical source? Where do
they get the defining it that way? Oh, because משה Moshe had
two kids. Of course who said משה Moshe was יצא yatza פרו
ורבו? pru urvu? Well presumably, you know, he wouldn't have stopped with
two boys, not two kids, two boys, had he not been יצא.
yatza. Okay, but
that's a but that is not telling us the logic behind it.
ובית הלל ילפינן מברייתו של עולם. u-Beit Hillel yalfina mi-briyato shel olam.
ובית הלל, Beit Hillel, as we see in the משנה, Mishnah, learns
out from how God created the world. So ובית שמאי לא יליף
מברייתו של עולם? u-Beit Shammai lo yalif mi-briyato shel olam? Why doesn't
בית שמאי Beit Shammai learn from that? Which is again fascinating like
that's not in the context of the מצוה, mitzvah, but nevertheless it's
a very powerful argument in itself about how God created the world
and the idea of procreating the world. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אין דנין אפשר משאי אפשר. ein danin efshar mishe-iy efshar. So
it's not just how God created the world, what's clear now that
the גמרא Gemara understands is it's also about how אדם וחוה Adam
ve-Chava had kids. God says to אדם וחוה, Adam ve-Chava, פרו ורבו
ומלאו את הארץ. pru urvu u-mil'u et ha-aretz. How what type of
kids did they have to have? All boys? All girls? No, they
had to have boys and girls. So the first fulfillment of פרו
ורבו pru urvu had to be boys and girls. So בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says yeah, that's not relevant because the world wouldn't have
gotten started without that. But now we don't have to worry about
the entire world and society and about there being enough boys and
enough girls in the world, that'll sort of take care of itself.
And that's not our responsibility and therefore it does not have to
be a boy and a girl. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
and because we're not in China. So the גמרא Gemara says ובית
הלל נמי לילף ממשה. u-Beit Hillel nami liyalef mi-Moshe. So why doesn't
בית הלל Beit Hillel learn from משה? Moshe? אמר לך משה מדעתיה
הוא דעבד. amar lach Moshe mida'atei hu de-avad.
No, you know, that was משה's Moshe's own decision, it is really
not the it was really not a model that anybody else could
follow. and he maybe wasn't מקיים פרו ורבו, me-kayem peru u-revu, והסכים
דעתו לדעת המקום, ve-hiskim da'ato le-da'at ha-Makom,
and his intent was in line with God's desire. פירש מן האשה,
pirash min ha-isha, I got panicked because we talked about שלשה דברים
עשה משה מדעתו והסכים דעתו לדעת המקום, shlosha devarim asa Moshe mi-da'ato
ve-hiskim da'ato le-da'at ha-Makom, three things Moshe sort of decided on his
own and it turned out that he was, that was what God
would have, God wanted. פירש מן האשה, pirash min ha-isha, he separated
from his wife after מתן תורה. Matan Torah. ושיבר הלוחות, ve-shiber ha-luchot,
he broke the לוחות. luchot. והוסיף יום אחד, ve-hosif yom echad, and
he added one day to the period leading up to מתן תורה.
Matan Torah. פירש מן האשה מאי דרש, pirash min ha-isha mai darash,
where did he get the idea to separate from his wife after
מתן תורה? Matan Torah? אמר אמר, amar amar, ומה ישראל שלא דיבר
עמהם שכינה אלא שעה אחת, u-mah Yisrael she-lo dibber imahem Shechinah ela
sha-ah achat, when God spoke to the Jewish people even for one
moment, וקבע להם זמן, ve-kava la-hem zman, and tell them only at
this time, from you know, from the time the שופר shofar blasts
and then it'll be over when the שופר shofar isn't blasting, אמרה
תורה אל תקרבו אל אשה, amra Torah al tikrevu el isha, they
weren't allowed to have sex leading up to it, אני שמיוחד לי
דיבור בכל שעה ושעה, ani she-meyuchad li dibbur be-chol sha-ah va-sha-ah, I
that God can speak to me at any time, I don't know
when God's going to speak to me, ולא קבע לי זמן, ve-lo
kava li zman, and I don't know ahead of time, you know,
when it's going to happen, על אחת כמה וכמה, al achat kamma
ve-chamma, how much more so do I have to constantly be ready
to that union with God and therefore I cannot be with my
wife? I cannot, I cannot have a sexual relationship with my wife.
I always have to be in a state of being prepared to,
you know, have the communion with God.
So, now how do we know והסכים דעתו לדעת המקום, ve-hiskim da'ato
le-da'at ha-Makom, how do we know God agreed to this? שנאמר, she-ne'emar,
because it says, לכו אמרו להם שובו לכם לאהליכם, lechu imru la-hem
shuvu la-chem le-oholeichem, go tell them go back to your tents, tents
meaning be with your wives. Again, speaking to the men. ואתה פה
עמוד עמדי, ve-attah poh amod immadi, but you stay here with Me,
which is being read as not just for the time being but
in a regular state of being, in an existential way, you're always
going to be standing with Me and ready to commune with Me
and therefore not back in your tent. ושיבר הלוחות מאי דרש, ve-shiber
ha-luchot mai darash, where do you see he broke the, the לוחות?
luchot? You know, where do you see that he sort of, you
know, how do we, where are we going to sort of again,
you know, we're sort of completely giving sort of saying we're not
looking, you know, what Moshe's thoughts were, we're not linking it to
a פסוק, pasuk, but we're sort of speculating or assuming what must
Moshe have been thinking that he thought it was the right decision
to break the לוחות? luchot? So אמר, amar, he said the following:
ומה פסח שהוא אחד משש מאות ושלש עשרה מצוות, u-mah Pesach she-hu
echad mi-shesh me'ot u-shlosh esreh mitzvot, ומה
פסח u-mah Pesach which is just one of 613, the Torah says
כל בן נכר לא יאכל בו, kol ben nechar lo yochal bo,
that a foreigner cannot eat from it. But a foreigner is defined
הלכתית halachically as somebody שנתנכרו מעשיו לאביו שבשמים, she-nitnacharu ma'asav le-aviv she-ba-shamayim,
somebody who has distanced himself from God, somebody who has violated the
Torah, not just a single violation, but somebody who has become like
rejected the Torah. So, so, where were we? התורה כולה, ha-Torah kullah,
the entire Torah, וישראל מומרים, ve-Yisrael mumarim, so if, so if it's
the entire
Torah and the Jewish people are a מומר, mumar, so על אחת
כמה וכמה, al achat kamma ve-chamma, how much more so should they
not be able to like receive the Torah, to receive the לוחות.
luchot. Of course that's pretty fun, you could say no, you may
be a מומר mumar you exclude from one thing, you don't exclude
from everything. But he sort of said no, if somebody is a
מומר mumar and they're excluded from the פסח, Pesach, how much more
so should they, you know, be excluded, not be able to be
accept the entire Torah and accept the לוחות. luchot. Okay. והסכים דעתו
לדעת המקום, ve-hiskim da'ato le-da'at ha-Makom,
and that was exactly what God had intended,
דכתיב אשר שברת, de-chtiv asher shibarta, that the, you know, the לוחות
luchot that you broke. ואמר ריש לקיש, ve-amar Reish Lakish, and so
he has a classic rabbinic wordplay, אשר שברת, asher shibarta, read it
the following way: יישר כחך ששברת. yishar kochacha she-shibarta. So אשר's asher
like, you know, שכוח, shkoach, שכוח, shkoach, like even though there's no,
you know, שכוח ששברת. shkoach she-shibarta.
All right, so it's pretty simple. Right?
The whole Torah was on the לוחות, luchot, which is not, not
as classic.
Right,
that's also true. Or somehow embedded in it. It's a good point
too. You know, the whole idea that you can categorize all 613
מצוות mitzvot under the Ten Commandments is a very, but it goes
all the way back to like Philo. It's a very early idea,
but you're right, in some ways it's implicit here seeing that, you
know, it could just be seen as like being representative of the
613, but maybe it's even suggesting somehow embedded in it are the
613.
One of the, one of the, one of the opinions, right, as
to what was on the לוחות, luchot,
it was the whole Torah. Yeah. So it goes like this. Okay.
הוסיף יום אחד מדעתו, hosif yom echad mi-da'ato, how about one day
before מתן תורה? Matan Torah? In other words that all these three
are in the context of מתן תורה Matan Torah for what that's
worth. Okay, he added one day of separation leading
up, דכתיב
וקדשתם היום ומחר, de-chtiv ve-kiddashtam hayom u-machar, prepare them today and tomorrow.
היום כמחר, hayom ke-machar, today has to be like tomorrow. Now today
already started.
So מה מחר לילו עמו, mah machar leilo immo, so the same
way tomorrow is a full day starting from the night before, אף
היום לילו עמו, af hayom leilo immo, so to get two days
it has to be two complete days starting from the night before.
So therefore, בלילה דאידנא נפק ליה, be-layla de-idanna nafak leh, but today
we're already past the, you know, last night. שמע מינה תרתי יומי
לבר מהאידנא, shema mina tartei yomei levar me-idanna, it must be two
days, two full days starting after today. והסכים דעתו לדעת המקום, ve-hiskim
da'ato le-da'at ha-Makom, and that was corresponding to God's intent. Okay, so
anyway all of that was a... yeah. By the way, take a
look a quick look at תוספות *Tosafot*: כולהו בישראל מומרים *Kuleihu be-Yisrael
mumarin*. תוספות *Tosafot* says: אין זה קל וחומר גמור
*Ein ze kal va-chomer gamur*, דשאני פסח
משום דקדשים *de-shany Pesach mishum de-kodshim*, אבל כל
התורה כולה אלו ויש לומדם ולהחזירם בתשובה *aval kol ha-Torah kullah elu
ve-yesh lomdam u-lehachziram bi-teshuvah*.
Right?
So it's a very bizarre קל וחומר *kal va-chomer* of the קרבן
פסח *Korban Pesach*. Okay, one מצוה Mitzvah, *mitzvah* to exclude you from
but it's a very big difference. Okay. Anyway, fine.
Now, but now the... anyway so that's the point, you can't learn
from משה *Moshe*. משה *Moshe* is a special case. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on. By the way, there are some ראשונים
*Rishonim* that think that ask: Would בית הלל *Beit Hillel* agree to
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*? When בית הלל *Beit Hillel* says a boy
and a girl, would בית הלל *Beit Hillel* say but you could
also be יוצא Yotzei *yotze* with two boys? So this... it's not
פשט Pshat *pshat* at all because we learned from בריאתו של עולם
*beri'ato shel olam* and שעה *sha'ah* and this whole point about משה
*Moshe* also indicates it because they're basically saying you can't learn from
משה *Moshe* which is basically to say according to me משה *Moshe*
wasn't יוצא Yotzei *yotze* פרו ורבו Pru u'revu, *peru u-revu*, but he's
an exception. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay. תניא *Tanya*,
we learn in a ברייתא *Baraita*: רבי נתן אומר בית שמאי אומרים
שני זכרים ושתי נקבות *Rabbi Natan omer Beit Shammai omrim shenei zecharim
u-shtei nekevot*. Now we have a different version of it. Talk about
a high birth rate. So בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* says you need
two boys and two girls. So he basically agrees to the idea
of boy and girl as procreation as the
key, but maybe the idea of פרו ורבו Pru u'revu, *peru u-revu*,
you know, פרו *peru* gets a boy and a girl, רבו *revu*
is double it. Okay. בית הלל אומרים זכר ונקבה *Beit Hillel omrim
zachar u-nekeva*, what we always knew, but a completely different version of
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*. אמר רב הונא מאי טעמא דרבי נתן אליבא
דבית שמאי *Amar Rav Huna mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Natan aliba de-Beit Shammai*,
דכתיב ותוסף ללדת את אחיו את הבל *dechativ va-tosef laledet et achiv
et Hevel*. So she continued to give birth to his brother, קין
*Kayin*'s brother הבל *Hevel*. So הבל ואחותו *Hevel ve-achoto*, את *et* is
understood to be like with a sister because there's no girls that
are described. Obviously there must have been girls but they're not described.
So it means הבל *Hevel* and his brother. And then it says
ותוסף *va-tosef*... I'm sorry, ותוסף ללדת את אחיו את הבל *va-tosef laledet
et achiv et Hevel*. So הבל *Hevel* and his sister, קין *Kayin*
and his sister. So since it says she did the same with
הבל *Hevel* as she did with קין *Kayin*, so we're going to
assume הבל *Hevel* had a sister and קין *Kayin* had a sister.
וכתיב *U-chtiv*, and then the פסוק *pasuk* says when she has שת
*Shet*: כי שת לי אלוהים זרע אחר תחת הבל כי הרגו קין
*ki shat li Elohim zera acher tachat Hevel ki harago Kayin*. Okay.
So God has given me another one because under הבל *Hevel* because
קין *Kayin* killed him. And why is that relevant? So if you
take a look at רש"י *Rashi* near the הגרסא ביה *hagarsa beh*,
but why הגרסא ביה *hagarsa beh*?
כי שתי זרע אחר תחת הבל *ki shati zera acher tachat Hevel*,
אמר תשלומין בעי *amar tashlumin ba'ei*, ולא סגיא בלא שני זכרים ושתי
נקבות *ve-lo sagya belo shenei zecharim u-shtei nekevot*.
Right? It sounded like we have to replace him. Now maybe she
just wants to replace him because you know, she wanted him as
a human being, as a human being. But no, it's understood the
reason she had שת *Shet* was because now that הבל *Hevel* is
dead she wasn't מקיים M'kayem *mekayem* the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah* anymore. So
she needed to have another kid. So and somehow we're assuming it
also means with a girl. All right, so that's how the גמרא
*Gemara* is sort of reading that story. The thing that I would
say also relevant is the question which the גמרא *Gemara* is going
to ask: If somebody has a boy and a girl and God
forbid one of his children you know die, does he have to...
was he already
יוצא Yotzei *yotze* or does he have to like leave behind a
boy and a girl, right? So that's... so here it's sounding like
she wasn't יוצא *yotze* anymore. So now she had to do this
to be יוצא *yotze*.
Okay. ורבנן *Ve-rabbanan*, and the Rabbis say no: אודויי הוא דקמודי
*oduyei hu de-kamodei*, she's just thanking God for giving her a new
child. It's not like "oh now I was יוצא *yotze*". Okay. תניא
אידך *Tanya idach*, we learn in another ברייתא *Baraita*: רבי נתן אומר
בית שמאי אומרים זכר ונקבה *Rabbi Natan omer Beit Shammai omrim zachar
u-nekeva*. Now we have another different version. בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* says
male and female what has for us been בית הלל *Beit Hillel*.
ובית הלל אומרים או זכר או נקבה *u-Veit Hillel omrim o zachar
o nekeva*. So one child, talk about a low birth rate. אמר
רבא מאי טעמא דרבי נתן אליבא דבית הלל *Amar Rava mai ta'ama
de-Rabbi Natan aliba de-Beit Hillel*, שנאמר לא תהו בראה לשבת יצרה Lo
tohu bera'ah lashevet yetzarah, *she-ne'emar lo tohu vera'ah lashevet yetzarah*.
So this is a פסוק *pasuk* that is used in the context
of פרו ורבו Pru u'revu? *peru u-revu* to talk about the purpose
of פרו ורבו Pru u'revu *peru u-revu* and what's fascinating by the
way about a lot of the halakhic issues around פרו ורבו Pru
u'revu. *peru u-revu* is normally we don't... we tend to think about
more technical questions. Well does the פסוק *pasuk* say איש *ish* and
אשה *ishah*, whatever, you know, or an אשה *ishah* חליצה *chalitzah*, קטן
*katan* doesn't do a חליצה *chalitzah*. By פרו ורבו Pru u'revu, *peru
u-revu* it's much more on the surface: what's the point of this
מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*? And when we figure out what's the point of
the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah* that's going to guide a lot of this
halakhic parameters, which is a pretty reasonable approach except that very often
in halakhic derivation it's that's not on the surface and it's usually
more technical issues. So here what the גמרא *Gemara* is saying is
and the use of the פסוק *pasuk* from ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* that God
did not create the world to be desolate but to be settled
is very much used in the context of understanding the purpose of
פרו ורבו Pru u'revu *peru u-revu*. So okay, but you would say
that should be a boy and a girl.
No. והא עבדי לה שבת *Ve-ha avdei lah shevet*, if you
even settled the world somewhat... necessarily repopulating the world or continuing to,
which is so fascinating because if you ask me which פסוק more
describes the purpose of פרו ורבו, Pru u'revu לא תהו בראה לשבת
Lashevet, יצרה, which emphasizes לשבת, to settle the world, or פרו ורבו,
Pru u'revu. what are the next words? מלאו את הארץ, Milu et
ha'aretz, right? So מלאו את הארץ Milu et ha'aretz
is much more כפילו K'feilu and you need to continue to procreate
and you know to continue that, that would much more point to
the boy and the girl. So it's interesting that this is now
taking precedence. Okay, איתמר, Itmar, it was taught. היו לו בנים בהיותו
עובד כוכבים ונתגייר. Hayu lo banim biyoto oveid kochavim v'nitgayer.
Somebody had children when they were non-Jews and then he converted. So
how much is a person fulfilled the מצוה, Mitzvah a) because he
has children even if he didn't sort of have them when he
was Jewish, and then it also gets to that whole biological question
about that הלכה Halacha doesn't, you know, sort of in those cases
does not see them as sort of being part of this person's
family legally being the person's children, but they are biologically the person's
children. By the way, that whole idea, you know, which I think
is often hard for us to get our head around, how can
they you know say they're not his kids? You know, think about
what happens in
you know in earlier in other societies about the whole idea of
bastard children, right? Bastard children was a biological child but was not
legally recognized as the person's child. Okay, so here by the question
somebody who converted and had biological children, they're not legally recognized as
his children but they are his biological children. Is that relevant for
פרו ורבו? Pru u'revu But he also also didn't have them when
he was Jewish. Are you, is there a מצוה Mitzvah פרו ורבו
Pru u'revu. on non-Jews? If you're יוצא as a non-Jew are you
יוצא as a Jew? Okay, so let's take a look.
היו לו בנים בהיותו עובד כוכבים ונתגייר. Hayu lo banim biyoto oveid
kochavim v'nitgayer.
רבי יוחנן אמר קיים פרו ורבו.
Rabbi Yochanan
amar kiyam pru u'revu.
You're מקיים M'kayem פרו ורבו. Pru u'revu ריש לקיש אמר לא קיים
פרו ורבו. Reish Lakish amar lo kiyam pru u'revu. You're not. רבי
יוחנן אמר קיים פרו ורבו דהוו ליה. Rabbi Yochanan amar kiyam pru
u'revu d'havu lei.
He has children, which both means a) biologically they're enough and that's
okay, and b) even though the actual having of them was when
he was not Jewish, now he still has them. Oh, okay, or
you could read it כשי K'she you know he was יוצא as
a non-Jew but it could also be that now he still has
them.
ריש לקיש אמר לא קיים פרו ורבו דכיון שנתגייר כקטן שנולד דמי.
Reish Lakish amar lo kiyam pru u'revu d'keivan she'nitgayer k'katan she'nolad dami.
They're not considered his kids anymore and therefore it's not relevant. Okay,
ואזלו לטעמייהו, V'azlu l'ta'ameihu, and they go according to their reasonings. דאיתמר
היו לו בנים בהיותו עובד כוכבים ונתגייר רבי יוחנן אמר אין לו
בכור לנחלה. De'itmar hayu lo banim biyoto oveid kochavim v'nitgayer Rabbi Yochanan
amar ein lo bechor l'nachalah. Okay, somebody had a biological kid as
a non-Jew and now he's converted and has a בכור, Bechor, his
first child as a Jew. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says he
doesn't have a status of בכור Bechor because he's not a biological
first child.
דהוו ליה ראשית אונו, D'havu lei reishit ono, the first of his
strength he had biologically. ריש לקיש אמר יש לו בכור לנחלה דכיון
שנתגייר כקטן שנולד דמי. Reish Lakish amar yeish lo bechor l'nachalah d'keivan
she'nitgayer k'katan she'nolad dami. No, it's like completely new, starting from a
clean slate and this is considered his first child. וצריכא, V'tzricha, you
need to have this debate in both cases. דאי אשמעינן בהא קמייתא,
D'ei ashm'inan bahai kammaita, if it was just a question of the
מצוה Mitzvah פרו ורבו, Pru u'revu בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן משום דמעיקרא
נמי בני פרו ורבו נינהו.
Bahai ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum de'mei'ikara nami
b'nei pru u'revu ninhu. It's one thing to say you're מקיים M'kayem
פרו ורבו pru u'revu, as a non-Jew because then it was in
the category of פרו ורבו pru u'revu. even as a non-Jew. Now
what does that mean? You could just say okay biologically you could
have kids even as a non-Jew. But what it also suggests is
not just the biological reality, it suggests that non-Jews maybe have a
מצוה Mitzvah פרו ורבו. pru u'revu. That's not such a big חידוש.
Chidush. For God's sake, God says it first to אדם וחוה, Adam
v'Chava, then God says it to נח, Noach, right, He sort of
says it to all of humanity. So to say that the מצוה
Mitzvah פרו ורבו pru u'revu. is on all of humanity is not
a big חידוש. Chidush. However, there are other גמרות Gemaras that suggest
not, and there's actually a fascinating מחלוקת ראשונים Machlokes Rishonim whether non-Jews
have a מצוה Mitzvu פרו ורבו. pru u'revu Let me ask you
a question: is it a מצוה Mitzvah to set up two non-Jews,
you know, to make a שידוך Shidduch between two non-Jews?
So פרו ורבו מלאו את הארץ, Pru u'revu milu et ha'aretz, right,
or is it and thinking about the point of פרו ורבו is
very different if you think about it as a מצוה mitzvah on
the Jewish people or you think about it as a מצוה mitzvah
on the entire world. So this גמרא very much suggests, which shouldn't
be a חידוש, Chidush, it's פשט of the entire of the תורה,
Torah, okay, I mean not just like a technical reading, it's the
whole point, it's a universal command that there's a מצוה mitzvah even
as non-Jews, although it's not listed like in the שבע מצוות בני
נח Sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach and so on, so that's why it's
debate there's a lot of debate around that. So that's what he
says. He says: Okay, it would be one thing to say you're
מקיים mekayem it as a non-Jew because it's not only they're biologically
your kids, but you were in the פרשה Parshah of the מצוה
mitzvah פרו ורבו then also. So it carries over now that you've
converted. אבל ענין נחלה דלאו בני נחלה נינהו, Aval inyan nachalah d'lav
b'nei nachalah ninhu, but by inheritance where they're not in the category
of inheritance. Now, of course non-Jews have laws of inheritance too, but
it means they're not in like the halachic categories of inheritance. So
דלאו בני נחלה נינהו, D'lav b'nei nachalah ninhu, where are we? אימא
מודי ליה לריש
לקיש, Eima modei lei l'Reish Lakish, maybe he'd agree with ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish that you start fresh when you convert. ואיתמר בהא, V'itmar
bahah, if you just had the case of inheritance, בהא קאמר ריש
לקיש. Bahah ka'amar Reish Lakish. That where ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
you start fresh because it's a completely new category of halakhic inheritance,
אבל בהאי, aval be-hai, but the case of פרו ורבו, אימא מודי
ליה לרבי יוחנן eima modi lei l'Rabbi Yochanan because
there it's more about biologically having kids and maybe non-Jews are in
the מצוה of having kids so maybe he would have conceded. צריכא,
tzricha, so you have to tell, so you see that it's a
debate, you have to say that they argued both cases. Okay, רש״י
Rashi says בני נח, bnei Noach, בני פרו ורבו נינהו, bnei pru
u'revu ninhu, דכתיב ויאמר להם פרו ורבו. d'chtiv vayomer lahem pru u'revu.
So רש״י Rashi sees them as part of, of course, God, you
know, whole creation has a מצוה of פרו ורבו. Okay, אייתי aiti
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Now רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan asks ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, בעת ההיא שלח ברודך בלאדן בן
בלאדן מלך בבל
ba-et ha-hee shalach Berodach
Baladan ben Baladan melech Bavel etc. So at that time, you know,
ברודך בלאדן, Berodach Baladan, the son of בלאדן, Baladan, the king of
בבל Bavel sent, sent etc. So
what do you see? So you see that
they recognize a sense of who your father is. So you see
non-Jews have a sense of who their father is, such a bizarre
proof, I think. אמר ליה amar lei he said, he said to
him, ביום קום עבודת כוכבים אית ליה, be-yom kum avodat kochavim it
lei,
I'm admitting that as non-Jews
you're considered not only a biological father but a legal father, but
נתגיירו לית ליה, nitgayeru leit lei,
once they convert that relationship is no longer legally recognized. Okay, אמר
ליה amar lei or אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, הכל מודים
בעבד שאין לו חיוס. hakol modin b'eved she-ein lo chiyus.
Everybody admits that with a slave who was then freed, had kids
as a slave and was then freed, that there is no, there
was no even recognized legal relationship even initially. So therefore there could
be no מצוה of פרו ורבו. דכתיב שבו לכם פה עם החמור,
d'chtiv shvu lachem po im ha-chamor,
sit here with the donkey, and the famous דרשה, drasha, עם הדומה
לחמור, am ha-domeh l'chamor,
with those that are similar to donkeys, which is not being said
here about all non-Jews, but is being said about slaves, understanding that
one of the people he took with him, one of them was
his slave. Okay, so therefore and of course as we know, certainly
happened in, not all slave societies, right? Some slave societies, they allowed
people to live as families, is that true? And in others like
in the South, right, they were not allowed to live as families,
right?
But certainly, they actually had conditional marriages until such time that you
were breaking up.
Interesting. Okay, so anyway, so the גמרא says as a legal point,
it was, you know, no sense of parentage was recognized, you know,
with slaves and therefore everybody agrees there that if a slave was
freed, what happened with his biological kids he would not fulfill פרו
ורבו. מיתיבי meitivei I'll ask you, וצבא חמישה עשר בנים ועשרים עבדים,
v'Tziba chamishah asar banim v'esrim avadim, ציבא Tziba had fifteen children and
twenty slaves. Why do I care that he had twenty slaves?
So, presumably it means that his twenty slaves were born from, right,
and רש״י Rashi says, I'm sorry, that wasn't the point. רש״י Rashi
says ציבא עבד כנעני של מפיבושת הוה. Tziba eved Kena'ani shel Mephiboshet
havah. So ציבא Tziba himself was a slave. Okay, and it says
he had twenty children, or fifteen children. So אמר רב אחא בר
יעקב, amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov,
כפרה בן בקרא. k'parah ben bikra. No, it's only describing it biologically,
right? Okay, like you say that this cattle had a sheep, or
this cattle had a calf. Okay, so when it says he had
fifteen children it doesn't mean they were his legal kids, it's just
saying he biologically he had fifteen children. Okay, אי הכי
הכא נמי, ee hachi hacha nami,
so if that's true,
one minute, let me just see the רש״י Rashi here. It says
something
about... Oh yeah, ברודך בלאדן, Berodach Baladan, right. So in any case,
why don't we ever assume that something indicates a sense of
legal parenting? Why don't we just say it all just means biological?
No, שאני התם דיחסינהו בשמיה ובשם אבוהון והכא לא מיחסו. shani hatam
d'yachsinhu b'shmey u'v'shem avuhon v'hacha lo miyachsu. No, there it said so-and-so
the son of so-and-so, which meant that it's legally recognized. So for
non-Jews parentage is legally recognized. Okay, the only question is what happens
when they convert. But for slaves it's just biological children, there's no
legal recognition of them as children. ואיבעית אימא v'iba'it eima if you
want I could say,
יחסינהו בדורתא אחריתי באבוה ובאבא דאבוה. yachsinhu b'dorta achriti b'avuhu u'v'abba d'avuhu.
It's even more than that because we see that they get, you
know, sort of attributed, you know, sort of identified not only with
the father but also grandfathers, so it's not just talking about their
biological offspring, there's a sense of parentage and family. Okay, דכתיב וישלח
המלך אסא בן הדד בן טברימון בן חזיון מלך ארם היושב בדמשק
לאמר d'chtiv vayishlach hamelech Asa ben Hadad ben Tavrimon ben Chezyon melech
Aram hayoshev b'Damesek l'emor etc. Okay, so by non-Jews as non-Jews there's
a legally recognized sense of father and child and so on, but
by slaves it's just biological. The question is when a non-Jew converts,
is the fact that he had the kids and that it was
legally recognized as his kids as a non-Jew and was מקיים mekayem
the מצוה of פרו ורבו as a non-Jew, does that then mean
that he continues to be מקיים it now that he has converted?
איתמר, itmar, it was said, וצריכי, v'tzrichi, I'm going to just read
a little bit more, היו לו בנים ומתו hayu lo banim u'metu
because this is the other half of the discussion. It goes back
to the חוה Chava case and it goes back to... What if
God forbid the kids predecease the person? So he had them but
they did not sort of continue to live. Is he מקיים פרו
ורבו *mekayem pru u'rvu* like the
גמרא *Gemara* spoke in terms of
the case of חוה *Chava* and הבל *Hevel*? So let's take a
look let's just read this very briefly. היו לו בנים ומתו *Hayu
lo banim umesu*. רב הונא אמר קיים פריה ורביה *Rav Huna amar
kiyem piryah u'rivyah*. You're מקיים *mekayem* because you had the kids. ורבי
יוחנן אמר לא קיים *v'Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kiyem*. You're not מקיים
*mekayem*. רב הונא אמר קיים משום דרבי אסי *Rav Huna amar kiyem
mishum d'Rabbi Assi* דאמר רבי אסי *d'amar Rabbi Assi* and now we
get to a question again of what is the מצוה *mitzvah* פריה
ורביה *piryah u'rivyah* about? How could you be מקיים פריה ורביה *mekayem
piryah u'rivyah* if you didn't leave your replacements behind? No, because פריה
ורביה *piryah
u'rivyah* is about something else, not just about populating the
world. Here's what it's about, רב אסי *Rav Assi*. דאמר רב אסי
אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו כל הנשמות שבגוף *d'amar Rav Assi
ein Ben David ba ad sheyichlu kol haneshamot shebaguf* שנאמר כי רוח
מלפני יעטוף *shene'emar ki ruach milifanai ya'atof*. בן דוד *Ben
David* משיח *Mashiach* won't come until all of the souls are used
up. Now בגוף *baguf* here doesn't mean in the body but גוף
*guf* is understood as like this storage facility up in heaven. There
are all these souls, unique souls, and they get distributed every time
a baby is born and when that storage warehouse is empty that's
when משיח *Mashiach* is going to come. So the מצוה *mitzvah* of
פריה ורביה *piryah u'rivyah* is to bring about משיח *Mashiach* to start
getting those souls used up. So therefore even חס ושלום *chas v'shalom*
if the kid dies you've still מקיים *mekayem* one of the goals
at least of פריה ורביה *piryah u'rivyah*. Okay so a very fascinating
new understanding of what פריה ורביה *piryah u'rivyah* is. רבי יוחנן אמר
לא קיים פריה ורביה *Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kiyem piryah u'rivyah* you're
not מקיים *mekayem*. לשבת יצרה בעינן והא ליכא *Lashevet yetzarah beinon v'ha
leika*. It's not just about having them born, it's about settling the
world and settling the world means that they're around to settle the
world. Okay now again it's a fascinating question. What would the
גמרא *Gemara* think if somebody had
kids and let's just say that לא קיים פריה ורביה *lo kiyem
piryah u'rivyah* if they die. So he had kids he's now 90
years old and his 70-year-old son dies. Is he not קיים פריה
ורביה *kiyem piryah u'rivyah*? Like if it's לשבת *lashevet* does it mean
that he has to predecease them? Or does it mean that they
have to have lived an adult life? Like at what stage are
you done? You know the joke? This couple 90 years old they
come to the judge for a divorce and the guy says 'I
don't understand, you've been married 70 years, happy marriage, all of a
sudden now you're 90 years old you come to a divorce? Why
now?' Says 'Your honor, we were waiting for the kids to die.'
So anyway alright
so we will continue with that tomorrow but it is again fascinating
in terms of thinking about how the idea of the goals of
פריה ורביה *piryah u'rivyah* might shape the מצוה *mitzvah* of פריה ורביה
*piryah u'rivyah* and its parameters. And I want to just end by
saying one very important idea that when רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says
you're not מקיים פריה ורביה *mekayem piryah u'rivyah* if you just have
the kids but it's also
about raising the kids and that is also extremely important in terms
of thinking
with couples that are being challenged with infertility about like is adoption
a way of being מקיים פריה ורביה *mekayem piryah u'rivyah*. And there
are definitely some פוסקים *poskim* that say that it's at least a
partial קיום *kiyum* because part of פריה ורביה *piryah u'rivyah* is not
just the having of the kids but the raising of the kids.
So a lot to think about. Okay see you all on Sunday.
Alright just like the end of history the end once you're done
you're done. Once we get there ברוך השם *baruch Hashem* we don't
have no more problems.